welcome to the class
today we are going to talk about
traditional methods for
machine learning in graphs and in
particular
what we are going to investigate is
different levels of tasks
that we can have in the graph in
particular we can think about the node
level prediction tasks
we can think about the link level or
edge level prediction tasks
that consider pairs of nodes and tries
to predict whether
the pair is connected or not and we can
think about graph level prediction
where we want to make a prediction for
an entire graph
for example for an entire molecule or
for
for an entire piece of code
the traditional machine learning
pipeline
is all about designing proper features
and here we are going to think of two
types of features we are going to assume
that nodes
already have some types of attributes
associated with them so this would mean
for example if this is a protein protein
interaction network
proteins have different um chemical
structure here different chemical
properties and we can think of this as
attributes attached to the nodes of the
network
at the same time what we also want to do
is we want to be able to
create additional features that will
describe
how this particular node is
positioned in the rest of the network
and what is its local
network structure and these additional
features that describe the topology of
the network of the graph
will allow us to make more accurate
predictions
so this means that we will always be
thinking about two types of
uh features structural features as well
as
features describing the attributes and
properties of the nodes
so the goal in uh in what we want to do
today is
especially focus on structural features
that will describe
the structure of a link in the broader
surrounding of the network that will
describe the structure
of the network neighborhood around the
given node of interest
as well as features that are going to
describe the structure
of the entire graph so that we can then
feed these features into machine
learning models
to make predictions traditionally
in traditional machine learning
pipelines we have two steps in the first
step
we are going to take our data points
nodes links
entire graphs um represent them um with
vectors of features and then on top of
that we are going then to train a
classical machine learning
uh classifier or model for example a
random forest
perhaps a support vector machine a feed
forward neural network
something of that sort so that then in
the future we are able to
apply this model where a new node link
or graph
appears we can obtain its features and
make a prediction so this is the setting
uh generally in which we are going to
operate today
so in this lecture we are going to focus
as i said on feature design
where we are going to use effective
features uh over the graphs
which will be the key to obtain good
predictive performance because we want
to capture the structure
the relational structure of the network
and traditional machine learning
pipelines use
hand-designed handcrafted features and
today's lecture
will be all about these handcrafted
features and we are going to split the
lecture into three parts
first we are going to talk about
features that describe individual nodes
and we can use them for node level
prediction then we are going to move and
talk about features that can
describe a pair of nodes and you can
think of this as features for link
level prediction and then we are also
going to talk about features and
approaches that describe topology
structure of entire graphs
so that different graphs can be compared
and
classified and for simplicity we are
going to
today focus on undirected graphs
so the goal will be how do we make
predictions for a set of objects of
interest
where the design choice will be that our
feature vector will be a d dimensional
vector
objects that we are interested in will
be nodes edges
sets of nodes uh milling entire graphs
and the objective function we'll be
thinking about is what are the labels
we are trying to predict so the way we
can think of this is that
we are given a graph as a set of
vertices as a set of edges
and we want to learn a function that for
example for every node
will give will give us a real valued
prediction
um which for example would be useful if
we are trying to predict
age of every node in our social network
and the question is
how can we learn this function f that is
going to make
these predictions so first we are going
to talk about
node level tasks and features that
describe individual nodes
the way we are thinking of this is that
we are thinking of this in what is known
as
semi-supervised case where
we are given a network we are given a
couple of nodes that are labeled with
different colors for example in this
case
and the goal is to predict the colors of
uncolored
nodes and if you look at this example
here so given the
red and green nodes we want to color uh
the gray nodes and you know if you
stare a bit at this the rule here is
that
uh green nodes should have at least two
edges adjacent to them while red nodes
have at least
one edge uh have exactly one edge
um connected to them so if we
are now able to describe um the node
degree of every node
um as a as a structural feature uh in
this graph
then we will be able to learn the model
that in this simple case
correctly colors the nodes of the graph
so we need features that will describe
this particular
topological pattern so the goal is
to characterize the structure
of the network around the given node as
well as in some sense the position the
location of the node
in the broader network context and we
are going to talk about
four different uh approaches that allow
us to do this
first we can always use the degree of
the node as a characterization of
um structure of the network around the
node
then we can think about the importance
the position of the node through the
notion
of node centrality measures and we are
going to review a few
then we will talk about um
characterizing the local network
structure
um not only how many uh edges a given
node has but also what is the structure
of the node around it
first we are going to talk about
clustering coefficient and then we are
going to
generalize this to the concept known
graphlets
so first let's talk about the node
degree we have already introduced it
there is nothing special but it is a
very useful feature
and many times it is quite important
where basically we will say
the we capture the the structure of the
node
v in the network with the number of
edges
that this node has um and you know the
drawback of this is that it treats
all the neighbors equally but in and in
this sense for example nodes with the
same degree
are indistinguishable even though if
they may be in different parts of the
network
so for example you know the node c and
node e
have the same degree so our classifier
won't be able to distinguish them or
perhaps node a
h e f and g also have all degree one
so they will all have the same feature
values so the our simple
machine learning model would that would
only use the node degree as a feature
would we only we would be able to
predict the same value
or would be forced to predict the same
value for all these
different nodes because they have the
same degree
so um to generalize be a bit this very
simple notion
we can then start thinking about um you
know no degree only counts
neighbors of the node and without
capturing let's say their importance or
who they really are
so the node centrality measures try to
capture characterize this notion of how
important
is the node in the graph and there are
many different ways how we can capture
or model this notion of importance i'm
quickly going to
introduce eigenvector centrality um
which we are going to further uh work on
and extend
to the seminal pagerank algorithm
later in the in the course i'm going to
talk about betweenness
centrality that will tell us how uh
how important connector a given node is
as well as closeness centrality that
will try to capture
how close to the center of the network a
given node is
um and of course there are many other um
measures of uh centrality or importance
so first let's define what is an
eigenvector centrality
we say that node v is as important
if it is surrounded by important
neighboring nodes u
so the idea then is that we say that the
importance of a given node v
is simply normalized divided by 1 over
lambda
sum over the importances of its
neighbors
in the network so the idea is the more
important my friends are
the higher my own importance is and
if you if you look at this and you write
it down you can write this
in terms of a simple matrix equation
where basically lambda is this
positive constant like a normalizing
factor c
is the vector of our centrality measures
a is now
a graph adjacency matrix and c is again
that vector of centrality measures
and if you write this in this type of
form then you see that this is a simple
um eigenvector eigenvalue equation
so what this means is that the solution
to this
problem here to this equation here um
is um um this is solved by the
uh uh by the given eigenvalue and the
associated eigenvector
and what people take as a uh
no a measure of node centrality is is
the eigenvector that is associated
with the largest um eigenvalue so in
this case if
eigen largest eigenvalue is lambda max
um
by perron-forbinious theorem uh because
we are thinking of the graph as
undirected it is always positive uh
and unique then uh the associated
leading eigenvector
c max is usually used as a centrality
score
uh for the nodes in the network and
again um the intuition is that
the importance of a node is the sum the
normalized sun
of the importances of the nodes that it
links to so
it is not about how many connections you
have but it is uh
how um who these connections point to
and how important
are those people so this is the notion
of node centrality captured by the
eigenvector
centrality a different type of
centrality that has a very different
intuition
and captures a different aspect of the
node's position in the network is
is what is called betweenness centrality
and betweenness centrality says that
node is important if it lies on many
shortest paths
between other pairs of nodes so the idea
is if a node is an important connector
an important bridge
an important kind of transit hub then it
has
a high importance the way we compute
between a centrality is to say between a
centrality of a given node v
is a summation over pairs of nodes uh
s and t and we count how many shortest
paths between
s and t uh pass through the node
v and we normalize that by the total
number of shortest paths
of the same length between s and t so
essentially
the more shortest paths a given node
appears on
the more important it is so it means
that this kind of measures
how good a connector or how good of a
transit point a given node is
so if we look at this example that that
we have here for example between the
centrality of these
uh nodes that are uh on the uh uh on the
edge of the network like a b
and e is zero but the the between the
centrality of node
c equals to three because the shortest
paths
from a to b pass through c a shortest
path
from a to d passes through c and a
shortest path
between uh a and e again passes through
c
so these are the three shortest paths
that pass through the note c
so it's between a centrality equals to
three and by a similar argument
the between the centrality of the node d
will be the same equals to three
here are the corresponding shortest
paths between different pairs of nodes
that actually pass through
this node d now
that we talked about how important
transit hub a given
node is captured by the betweenness
centrality
the third type of centrality that again
captures a different
aspect of the position of the node is
called closeness
centrality and this notion of centrality
importance
says that a node is important if it has
small
shortest path path lengths to add all
other nodes in the network so
essentially
the more central you are the shorter the
path to everyone else
is the more important you are the way we
operationalize this is to say that the
closeness centrality of a given node v
is one over the sum of the shortest path
lengths
between the node of interest v and any
other node
u in the network so uh to give an
example
right the idea here is that the the
smaller this
um the the more in the center you are
the smaller the summation will be
so one over a small number will be a big
number and if somebody is on the
let's say very far on the edge of the
network and needs a lot of
uh uh long paths to reach other nodes in
the network
then it's between a centrality will be
low because the sum of the shortest path
lengths
will be high in this case for example
you know the
the closeness centrality of node a
equals 1 8
because um it has to node b
it has the shortest path of length 2 to
node c it has a shortest path of length
to d it is 2 and 2e is 3. so it's
1 8. while for example the node d that
is a bit more in the center of the
network
has a length 2 shortest path to node a
and length 1
shortest paths to all other nodes in the
network so this is one over five
so it's between a centrality oh sorry
it's cl node centrality closest
centrality
uh is higher um and then
now i'm going to shift gears a bit i was
talking about centralities in terms of
how how important what is the position
of the node in the network now we are
going to start talking we are going back
to think about
the node degree and the local structure
uh around the node and when i say local
structure it really means that for a
given node we only look
uh in its immediate vicinity uh and
decide
uh on the uh pro on the and characterize
the properties of the network around
it and a classical measure of this is
called clustering
coefficient and clustering coefficients
measures how connected one's neighbors
are
so how connected the friends of node v
and the way we define this is to say
clustering coefficient
of node v is the number of edges among
the
neighboring nodes of v divided by
the degree of v choose 2. so this is
the number this is um k choose 2
measures how many pairs
can you select out of k different
objects so this is saying
how many how many note pairs there exist
in your neighborhood so how many
potential edges are there in the net in
in your
neighborhood um and this says
how many edges actually occur
so this metric is naturally between zero
and one where
zero would mean that none of your
friends not on none of your
connections know each other and one
would mean that all your friends are
also friends with each other
so here's an example imagine this simple
graph on
five nodes and we have our uh red node
v to be the node of interest so for
example in this case
node v has clustering coefficient um of
one
uh because all of its uh four friends
are also uh connected uh with each other
so here
um the clustering is one in this
particular case for example the
clustering is uh
0.5 the reason being that out of
um six possible connections between the
four neighboring nodes of node v there
are only
uh three of them are connected while
here in the last example the clustering
is zero
because um out of uh all four
uh neighbors of uh node v none of them
are connected
with each other the observation that is
interesting
that then leads us to generalize uh this
notion
to the notion of clustering coefficient
to the notion of graphlets
the observation is that clustering
coefficient basically counts the number
of triangles
in the ego network of the node so let me
explain what i mean by that
first ego network of a given node is
simply a network that is induced by the
node
node itself and its neighbors so it's
basically degree
one neighborhood network around the
given node
and then what i mean by counts triangles
i mean that now if i have this ego
network of a node i can count
how many triples of nodes are connected
and in this particular use case where
the clustering coefficient of this nose
is 0.5 it means that i find
three triangles in the
network neighborhood in the
ego network of my node of interest so
this means that clustering coefficient
is really counting these
triangles which in social networks are
very important because in social
networks
a friend of my friend is also a friend
with me so social networks
naturally evolve by triangle closing
where basically the intuition is
if somebody has two friends in common
then more or less
sooner or later these two friends will
be introduced by this node v
and there will be a link uh forming here
so social networks tend to have a lot of
triangles in them and
clustering coefficient is a very
important metric
so now with this the question is could
we generalize this notion of
triangle counting uh to more interesting
structures
and and count uh the number of
pre-specified graphs
in the neighborhood of a given node and
this is exactly
what the concept of graphlet captures
so the last
way to characterize the structure of the
of the network around the given node
will be through this concept of
graphlets
that rather than just to count triangles
also counts other types of structures
around the node
so let me define that so graphlet is a
rooted connected non-isomorphic
sub graph so what do i mean by this for
example here are all
um possible graphlets um that
that have um a different number
of nodes we start with a graph let on
two nodes so it's basically nodes
connected by an edge there are
three possible graphlets on three nodes
and there is a and then here are the
graphlets of
four nodes and these are the graphlets
on five nodes
so now let me explain what we are
looking at so for example
if you look at the graphlets on three
nodes it is either
a chain on three nodes or it's a
triangle right it's all three nodes are
connected these are all
possible connected graphs on three nodes
now why do i say there are uh three
graphlets not two
uh the reason for that is that the
position of the node of
interest also matters so here for
example you can be at
this position and then the question is
in how many graphs
like this do you participate in or you
can be at this other
uh position here position number two and
it's basically saying
how many pairs of friends do you have
and then this
this in the case of a triangle all these
positions are isomorphic they are
equivalent so there is
only one of them so this is the position
in which you may
you can be now similarly if you look at
now at uh four node graphlets there is
uh
many more of them right um they
they look the following right you again
have a chain on four nodes and you have
two positions on the chain you're either
in the edge or you are
one one away from the edge from if you
go from the other end
it is just symmetric here in the second
this kind of star graph
like you can either be the satellite on
the edge of the star or you can be the
center of the star
in a in a square all the positions are
isomorphic so you can be just
part of the square here's another
interesting um
example where it has three different
positions you can be you can be here
you can be here or you can be at
position 10 which is isomorphic to the
to the other side
in this kind of square with that
diagonal again you have uh two different
positions
and in this last fully connected graph
on four nodes
uh all nodes are equivalent so there is
all positions are equivalent so there is
only one
so what this shows is that um if you say
how many graphlets are there on five
nodes
uh there is 73 of them right labeled
from
1 all the way to 73 because it's
different graphs as well as positions in
these graphs
so now that we know what the graphs are
we can define what is called
graph led degree vector which is
basically a graph let
base based features for nodes
and graph led degree counts
the number of times a given graphlet
appears
rooted at that given node so the way you
can think of this is
degree counts the number of edges that
the node touches
clustering coefficient counts the number
of triangles
that a node touches or participates in
and
graph the degree vector counts the
number of graphlets
that that a node participates in
so to give you an example um
a graphic degree vector is then simply a
count vector
of graph let's rooted at that given node
so
to uh to give an example consider this
particular graph here and we are
interested in the
node v then here is a set of graphlets
on
two and three nodes this is our universe
of graphlets we are only
going to look at the graphlets all the
way up to size of three nodes and not
bigger
um and then uh you know what are the
what are now the graphlet instances for
example the
the graphlet of type a this node v
participates in two of them right it
one is here and the other one is there
right so this means this one and that
one
then the graphlet of type b node v
participates in one of them right this
is
um this is the graphlet here right
b and then you say how about how many
graphs of type d
does uh node um sorry of type c
does node v participate in and it
doesn't participate in any because uh
here it is but these two nodes are also
connected
so because graphlets are induced
this edge appears here as well so for d
we get zero
sorry for c we get zero how about for d
d is a path of on two nodes if you look
at it
there are two instances of d uh here is
one
and uh here is the other as illustrated
here
so graphlet degree vector for node v
would be 2 1 0 2 so
2 one zero two and this now
characterizes
the local neighborhood structure uh
around
the given node of interest based on the
frequencies of these graphlets that the
node v
participates in so
um if we consider graphlets from
two to five nodes we can now describe
every node in the network with a vector
that has 73 dimensions or 7 3
73 coordinates and this is essentially a
signature of a node that describes the
topology
of node's neighborhood and it captures
its inter interconnections um all the
way
up to the distance of four four hops
right because um
uh a chain of four edges has five nodes
so if you are at the edge of the chain
which means you count how many paths of
length
four uh lead out of that node so it
characterizes the network
up to the distance of four and a graph
like degree vector provides a measure of
node's
local network topology and comparing
vectors now
of two nodes pro provides a more
detailed measure
of local topological similarity than for
example just
looking at node degree or clustering
coefficient so this gives me
a very fine-grained way to compare the
neighborhoods uh the structure of
neighborhoods
of two different nodes in perhaps two
different
networks so to conclude uh
so far we have introduced different ways
to obtain node features
and they can be categorized based on
importance features like node degree and
different centrality measures
as well as structure based features
where again no degree is like the
simplest one
then that counts edges clustering counts
triangles
and the graphlet degree vector is a
generalization that counts
other types of structures that a given
node of interest
participates in so to summarize
the importance based features capture
the importance of a node in a graph
we talked about degree centrality
and we talked about different notions of
centrality closeness betweenness
as well as the eigenvector
centrality and these types of features
are using
in predicting for example how important
or influential are nodes in the graph so
for example
identifying celebrity users in social
networks would be
one such example
the other type of node level features
that we talked about
were structure-based structure based
features that capture the topological
properties of local neighborhood
around the node we talked about node
degree clustering coefficient
and graph led degree vector and these
types of features are very useful
uh for predicting a particular node's
role
uh in the network so for example if you
think about
predicting protein function then um this
type of graphlet
features are very useful because they
characterize
the structure of the network around a
given
node